<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A candle lighted at a coal from the altar whereby the King and rulers of this nation with the people of this present age may see the stone on which many have stumbled, and the rock which hath broken to pieces unfaithful men once in authority, who instead of protecting, did persecute the people of God, when they had the high places of the earth in possession, and that these present rulers may take warning betimes, least they stumble at the same rock, and while they have opportunity they may rather become as nursing-fathers to the flock of God within these dominions, by giving due encouragement to tender consciences, and men fearing God as in matters of religion / and this is directed unto you by a subject of the King of Righteousness, Tho. Salthouse.</title>
            <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12594307</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12594307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64021</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64021)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 702:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A candle lighted at a coal from the altar whereby the King and rulers of this nation with the people of this present age may see the stone on which many have stumbled, and the rock which hath broken to pieces unfaithful men once in authority, who instead of protecting, did persecute the people of God, when they had the high places of the earth in possession, and that these present rulers may take warning betimes, least they stumble at the same rock, and while they have opportunity they may rather become as nursing-fathers to the flock of God within these dominions, by giving due encouragement to tender consciences, and men fearing God as in matters of religion / and this is directed unto you by a subject of the King of Righteousness, Tho. Salthouse.</title>
                  <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64021:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64021:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Candle lighted At a Coal from the ALTAR, Whereby the KING and RULERS of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the People of this preſent Age may ſee the STONE on which many have ſtumbled, and the ROCK which hath broken to pieces unfaithful men once in Authority, who inſtead of protecting, did perſecute the People of God, when they had the High Places of the Earth in poſſeſſion. And that theſe preſent Rulers may take warning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, leaſt they ſtumble at the ſame Rock, and while they have opportunity they may rather become as Nurſing-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Flock of God within theſe Dominions, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving due encouragement to tender Conſciences, and men fearing God as in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>And this is directed unto you by a ſubject of the King of Righteouſneſs, THO. SALTHOUSE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zeph. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſs that I will ſearch <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Candles, and puniſh the men that are ſetled upon their Lees, that ſay in their hearts, The Lord will not do good, neither will he do evil.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64021:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64021:2"/>
            <p>THE Viſion of all hath been as the words of a Book ſealed, which could neither be read by the learned nor unlearned, for no man in Heaven nor in Earth was found worthy to open the Book and to looſe the Seals and to read thereon but the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah, that root and off-ſpring of <hi>David</hi> who hath prevailed to open it; and darkneſs hath covered all the Kingdoms of the world, and all the Kindreds of the Earth for many ages and generations, and the Great Whore arayed in Purple and Scarlet colour, and decked with gold and ſilver and pretious ſtones, hath had her ſeat upon the waters which is multitudes and peoples and tongues and languages, having in her hand a golden Cup filled with abominations and with the filthineſs of her fornication, and with her the Kings and Inhabitants of the Earth have committed ſpiritual fornication, and have drunk of the Wine of her fornication, and they have given their power unto the Beaſt and the falſe prophet who maketh War againſt the Lamb and his followers; and they have drunk the blood of the Martyrs and Saints, and have by their Lawes compelled all, both free and bond, high and low, rich and poor to receive that mark of the Beaſt, and to bow down and worſhip his Image; but the faithful witneſſes that had the Teſtimony of Jeſus and the Word of God, who could not for Conſcience ſake bow to the Image of the Beaſt, nor receive his mark, have they ſlain in the ſtreets of that great City ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt alſo was crucified by the Princes of the Gentiles who did not know him, and by force and violence in theſe laſt dayes and perilous times ſince there hath been a departing from the Faith once delivered unto the Saints, have the Princes of this world exerciſed Lordſhip over the heritage of God, by compelling and forcing people ignorantly to worſhip the unknown God in the Idols Tempels under pains and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of baniſhment, burning, ſtigmatizing, ſtoning to death, impriſonment and the like; and all the penalties infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon and ſuſtained by the Servants of God and Saints of the Moſt High, hath been by vertue of Authority derived from the higher Power, or from men in holy Order as they have been ſtiled; ſo that all the perſecution of tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64021:3"/>and of the Prophets and Saints about Religion, and Religious exerciſes have been and may juſtly be charged upon the higher Power and holy Church ſo called; and all that have been caſt into Priſon for the Teſtimony of Jeſus and the Word of God hath been in the name of the higher Power, and all that have ſuffered the ſpoiling of their goods, and the loſs of liberty and eſtates, for not putting into the hireling Prieſts mouths, hath been by the higher Powers as in the behalf of God and holy Church, and many have ſuffered for theſe things as it hath been ſaid in his Highneſs his name in this laſt time of Apoſtacy, in which the day hath been dark over the Prophets, that they have not had any Viſion or Anſwer of God nor Revelation from him, but have denyed Revelation and immediate Inſpiration, and have been in darkneſs and blindneſs as in the land of the ſhadow and death, by whoſe inſtigation cruel yokes of bondage have been impoſed upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God in this long night of darkneſs and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but in patience have we waited for him whoſe coming was prepared as the morning, and in anſwer to our earneſt expectation in an acceptable time, when there was none to help, the Arm of the Lord was made bare to bring Salvation.</p>
            <p>And now the Everlaſting Day-ſtar hath appeared, and the God of all the Families of the Earth is bringing a remnant of Righteous Souls out of that <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs which hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the whole earth in the time of Antichriſts Reign, and from under that thick vail which hath been ſpread (over this) and all Nations, hath the Lord delivered a People that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were walking in darkneſs, and wandring from Mountain to Mountain in the night of Apoſtacy, as old <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the cloudy and dark day, like ſheep without a ſhepherd, and as <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh was delivered from their great bondage and hard ſervitude in outward <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> even ſo hath the Lord called, and by his own Arm gathered his People out of ſpiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they long mourned in deſolation under the power of a ſtrange King and cruel Task-maſters; and this people are fully perſwaded in their minds not to return back into <hi>Egypt</hi> again, but to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel on through the Kingdoms of <hi>Edom,</hi> &amp; the borders of <hi>Moab,</hi> until they come to the promiſed Land which is purchaſed to be a poſſeſſion and peaceable habitation for them and their off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſping from generation to generation.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64021:3"/>
            <p>And this people whom the Lord hath called out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his marvellous light, are a diſpiſed people, miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to men in Authority, as diverſe in their Lawes and Cuſtoms from all other people, and they are reproached with that name of diſtinction which is the Object of their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries indignation, being reproachfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe they tremble at the Word of the Lord and walkes humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; and ſince the time that the Lord hath appeared for our Salvation and Deliverance out of darkneſs, bondage and captivity, and ſince we ſet our faces towards <hi>Zion</hi> the City of Truth, we have been tryed with cruel mockings, bonds and impriſonments, and we have born the reproaches of <hi>Moab,</hi> and the revilings of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> yea both <hi>Gabel Ammon</hi> and <hi>Ameleck</hi> have ſet themſelves in oppoſition againſt Gods peculiar treaſure, and the uncircumciſed in heart and eares <hi>Aſhur</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtians</hi> hath joyned with them to help the inceſtuous children of Lot in their cruelty, perſecution and oppoſition againſt the Lords Servants, thoſe weak things of the world whom he hath choſen to place his Name among, and theſe poor of the world whom he hath made rich in Faith.</p>
            <p>But he that reproved Kings for the ſake of his people, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Touch not mine annointed, and do my Prophets no harm, hath ſmitten ſome of our Adverſaries and oppoſers with a deadly wound, and with Equity will he plead the Cauſe of the oppreſſed that have no helper in the Earth.</p>
            <p>Therefore hearken unto this Word ye Heads and Rulers of the people, and give ear O Houſe of the King, and all you in Authority, whether in Church or State, or of matters ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or temporal, this is the Word of the Lord God unto you in this your day of Tryal, touch not the Lords annointed, nor offend not any of thoſe little ones who are coming up out <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> neither ſeek to ſet up your ſelves as Lords over Gods Heritage, by making Laws or preſcribing wayes of worſhip to impoſe upon thoſe tender Conſciences and thoſe Righteous Souls contrary to the ſpiritual Law of God (according to his promiſe) written in their hearts; for behold the day is come in which the Lord is putting his Spirit in the inward parts, and writing his Law in the hearts and in the mindes of his people, ſo that we cannot ſubmit to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64021:4"/>Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and the <hi>Perſians,</hi> nor bow down to worſhip <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image at the ſound of the Muſick, whether Bell, Organs, Drum or Trumpet, neither can we conform to the old Antichriſtian Traditions which in the time of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was taught for Doctrines and Church Ordinances, and impoſed upon our Fore-fathers to be obſerved by them under pains, penalties and corporal puniſhments, neither can we worſhip or bow down to the reſemblance or likeneſs of any thing either in Heaven above or in the Earth beneath, nor in the waters under the Earth, leaſt we ſhould provoke the Lord to jealouſie, who will not give his glory to another, nor we cannot have mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or for fear of perſecution, knowing that he who reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth perſons doth commit ſin, and is convinced of the Law as a tranſgreſſor.</p>
            <p>Wherefore all you that are in Authority ſet up to Rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men as Magiſtrates, whether ſpiritual, Military or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, remember what the Rock of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath ſaid, He that Rules amongſt men muſt be Juſt, ruling in the Fear and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, that he may be a terrour to the evil-doers, and a praiſe to them that do well; and if you thus rule for God in his fear, then will your light go forth as a morning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out clouds, and thoſe under your Government will revive as the Corn, and ſpring up as the tender graſs out of the earth, by clear ſhining after the rain, and you muſt fear God and work Righteouſneſs, and hate oppreſſion and covetouſneſſe, elſe you cannot pleaſe God nor Rule for him amongſt men, neither can your Government be bleſſed, nor of long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, except you be Wiſe and Learned, Juſt and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Holy and Humble, Gentle and eaſie to be entreated; therefore be inſtructed O King and all ye Rulers of the earth, and ſerve the Lord with fear, and walk humbly before him, for humility goeth before true honour, and except you be Humble, Holy and Upright you cannot be owned or accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the honourable of the earth, although (for a ſeaſon) you have the high Places thereof in poſſeſſion to prove and try you as others have bin that were before you, whom the Lord hath caſt out &amp; rejected from bearing Rule amongſt men (not alone for your ſakes) but becauſe of their unfaithfulneſs to the Lord in their day, and the heavy yoaks which they laid
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64021:4"/>upon the necks of thoſe over whom they bore Rule, and by reaſon of their envy, violence and unkindneſs unto thoſe ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who are paſſing thorow your bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders out of the houſe of bondage, who did deſire nothing of them nor now of you, but to paſs peaceably by the high way which is caſt up and prepared for the Redeemed of the Lord out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> to that holy City whoſe Builder and Maker is God, where they may worſhip God in the Spirit and Truth, in the beauty of holineſs; and now let it enter into your Conſideration, that the Lord hath had a remnant of Righteous Servants in this Nation, that have not defiled their garments with the deteſtible things, nor with the abominations that have been committed in the land, and that have not bowed their knee unto <hi>Baal;</hi> and theſe are they that trembles at the Word of the Lord, and they have been alwayes grieved and oppreſſed by reaſon of the great evils and abominations that have been committed in the land, not onely open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, pride and wantonneſs among the baſer ſort, but alſo in things relating to Religion and the Worſhip of God, and Church Ordinances (ſo called) and the Spirit of Grace and Truth which is poured forth from on high, and which reſts upon them, hath ſtrove from time to time with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of this Nation for Freedom and Liberty of Conſcience in matters of ſuch weighty concernment as the Work &amp; Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and ſometimes the Cry thereof hath entred into the ears of King, Parliaments &amp; others in Authority, and then they would promiſe or at leaſt pretend a Reformation in Church and State, and much action hath been in this Nation in a few years laſt paſt, and the Lord hath overturned one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment after another without either Bow, Battel-Ax or outward Weapon, but not without giving them warning by his Watch-men, either in word or writing, for they have had precept upon precept, and line upon line, and the Lord hath pleaded with them by his Judgements, and when his hand hath been upon them, then they would humble themſelves for a ſeaſon, and ſet upon doing ſomething in anſwer to the expectation of that Spirit that did ſtrive with them; but it may and alwayes hath been obſerved, that the people in whom this oppreſſed Spirit did ſtrive and operate moſt of all, and who were moſt zealous for a Reformation they have alwayes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64021:5"/>been accounted as Hereticks and Sectaries, and reproached with the names of Puritans, Round-heads, and Quakers, and ſuch like brands of reproach as might render them odious to men in Authority, or as a diſcontented people not fit to live upon the Earth, yet nevertheleſs the witneſs of God in the Conſciences of Men in places of truſt hath ſomtimes anſwered to the cry of the oppreſſed, ſo that they began to remove ſome Antichriſtian Yoaks of Bondage out of the way, which was the greateſt burden to tender Conſciences; as for inſtance ſeveral Monuments of Idolatry and Superſtition was aboliſhed, all repreſentations of the perſons of the Trinity, Angels or Saints in or about the Cathedral, Collegiate or Pariſh Church or Chappel (ſo called) and the High Altars taken down, and all Superſtitious Veſtments, as Copes, Surplices, Roods, Holy Water, Funts, Croſſes, Crucifixes, and Pictures defaced, and no more to be uſed in or about the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe ſeveral Clauſes and Articles of Ordinances and Acts of Parliament repealed which did impoſe Penalties upon people for not coming to Pariſh Churches, for not keeping Holy Daies, and for not hearing the Common Prayer, with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties enjoyned to be impoſed upon ſuch as ſhould uſe or read the Common Prayer in any Church, or Chappel, or private Family, as may appear by ſeveral Ordinances and Acts of Parliament about that Year (44) and many Carnal invented Ordinances of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as ſprinkling infants at the Funt, finging before the dead, bowing to the high Altar, rails about the Communion Tables, and abundance of ſuch like things relating to the Worſhip and Service of God which was known to be but meer ſcraps and Rags of Popery, were denied, as beggarly Elements and rudiments of the world, and no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Jeſus Chriſt to be practiſed among the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</p>
            <p>Now theſe were good beginnings in order towards a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in ſpiritual things, and in relation to Church Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but alas, we have ſeen many good appearances, and ſuch fair promiſes come to little or nothing, that we are jealous with a Godly Jealouſie leſt the old Serpent ſhould deceive theſe Rulers, and draw them back into bondage again in things of this Nature as he hath done them that formerly had the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and diſpoſing of the great Affairs of this Kingdom, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64021:5"/>promiſed a Reformation both in Church and State, and yet after theſe old corrupted Popiſh Ceremonies and Laws, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to ſpiritual Cognizance ſo called was aboliſhed by the King, Parliament, Protector and his Councel, they ſoon fell from thoſe good beginnings, and ſought to ſet up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their own Intereſts, and then Religion was little regarded, but as a Cloak for them to carry their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns under, and when they were ſetled in the high places, then Magiſtrates and the Prieſts of the high Places conſulted and took Councel together againſt the Lord and againſt his Annointed, and inſtead of the old ſuperſtitious Laws and Ordinances they began to make new Laws to limit the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to their Directions and Preſcriptions, and Obſervations, by which the Servants and Handmaids of the Lord, whoſe Conſciences were tender, and could not deny one Form to take up another inſtead thereof, was haled before their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seats, and ſomtimes whipped, perſecuted, fined, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for reproving ſin in the Gates, for not ſwearing, for meeting together in the fear of the Lord, &amp; ſuch like things, until the Lord pleaded with the Rulers and viſited for thoſe things, and made that Rock againſt which they ſtrove and could not prevail, a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a Rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence on which they are fallen and broken to pieces.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>King Charles</hi> the firſt, and his Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament, took away the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Court when they ſaw the many harms and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that were in it, and that it was a great ſnare and a bondage to tender Conſciences, and aboliſhed ſeveral Acts and Ordinances, that did bind people in an uniformity thereunto, as may at large appear by an Act of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begun and held at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the third of the ninth month called <hi>November</hi> in the year (1649.) In which Act it is expreſſed that no Arch Biſhop, Biſhop, nor Vicar-general, nor no Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Judg exerciſing Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Power or Authority ſhall by any grant, licenſe, or Commiſſion of the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs or Succeſſors from and after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>41. inflict any pain, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, or fine, amercement, impriſonment, or other Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment upon any of the Kings Subjects for any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64021:6"/>matter or thing whatſoever belonging to Spiritual Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance or Juriſdiction, and that they ſhall not adminiſter any Corporal Oath whereby any may be forced to confeſs or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelves in any offence, whereby they are liable or expoſed to any cenſure, pain, penalty or puniſhment, on a ſpiritual account, upon pain that every perſon who ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend contrary to the Act above mentioned, ſhall forfeit and pay treble dammage to every perſon thereby grieved, and the ſum of 100 pound to him or them, who ſhall firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or ſue for the ſame: Now this was a Legal Authority, and this Act remains in as full force and vertue, as if there had been no interruption of that power, or as if it had been made by the King and Parliament now in being, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be expected that the Kings Subjects ſhall not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any penalty for not ſwearing, or upon any ſpiritual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whatſoever, for the King hath diſcharged all Judges and Miniſters of Juſtice in the name of himſelf, his Heirs, and Succeſſors not to impoſe any Oath, pain, penalty or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any perſon or perſons, male or female, as upon a ſpiritual account; and if the Kings Succeſſors ſhall put this Law in execution, it will be ſome eaſe to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, and will give the good people of theſe Nations hopes, that a Reformation may yet be wrought and compleated in this Nation after all theſe ſtrange altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and overturnings, though it is contrary to the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of many from any thing that appears viſible.</p>
            <p>Conſider in time what the Lord God requires at your hands, who are now intruſted with the Government, and bring not upon the Nation the old Antichriſtian yoak of bondage, which neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear, let Chriſt Jeſus the Everlaſting high Prieſt who is the ſouls Biſhop, have the whole power in the Church as the head of it, and let him order all things therein according to his Heavenly Wiſdom and wonderful Councel, both as to the Calling, Ordination, and ſending forth Miniſters, to preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, and Paſtors according to his own heart and mind, that the people may be fed with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and underſtanding, and let theſe Miniſters ſent forth by Chriſt who have the mind of Chriſt, and do abide in his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64021:6"/>Doctrine, have free Liberty without perſecution to preach the Goſpel in all the Provinces of theſe Dominions, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no Judg nor Miniſter of Juſtice to inflict any Penalty or Corporal puniſhment upon them on this ſpiritual account, nor to caſt them into priſon for the Teſtimony which they hold, and which is agreeable to the Teſtimony of Jeſus, the Word of God, and Scripture of Truth, for it is both againſt the Law of God, &amp; alſo againſt the good Laws of this Nation that any man ſhould ſuffer puniſhment, perſecution or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment on any Religious or Spiritual account whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Therefore let the world know, even your adverſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that you are of the Chriſtian Religion, by giving due encouragement to tender Conſciences, and to Chriſts Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to preach the Word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon without moleſtation or interruption, by any colour or pretence of Authority derived from that higher Power.</p>
            <p>For he who aſcended up on high, who led Captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, hath given gifts unto men for the work of that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, that there may not be a famine of hearing the Word in this Nation; and foraſmuch as the Lord hath ſpoken, we cannot but Propheſie &amp; Declare of the things which we have ſeen and heard, and that which we have taſted and handled of the Word of life, that people may be turned from the darkneſs to the light, and from the power of Satan unto God; and it is the Command of Chriſt unto his Miniſters, that as they have freely received they muſt freely give, that the Goſpel may be made without charge, and it muſt be freely preached, not for filthy lucre ſake, but of a ready mind; and a neceſſity hath laid upon the Miniſters of Chriſt in theſe laſt dayes and perilous times (though the more they love the leſs they are beloved again) to reprove ſin in the Gates, and to give warning to Magiſtrates and men in Authority both in word and writing by way of admonition, exortation, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom advice and counſel, that in the fight of the Lord they may be clear of the blood of all men, and that all might be left without excuſe in that day when God ſhall Judge the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of men by Jeſus Chriſt according to the Goſpel; and becauſe Judgement hath been turned backward, and good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64021:7"/>Councel rejected by Protector, Parliaments and others once in Authority, and the Servants of the Lord cruelly perſecuted by whom it was directed to them; therefore hath the Lord rejected them from bearing the Sword of juſtice; and now you are ſet as at the ſtearn of Government, and this is your day of Tryal, and the Lord God will prove you &amp; try you whether you will be a terrour to the evil-doers, and a praiſe to them that do well, or limit his Spirit as others have done before you; and if you expect ſubjection to your power, you muſt Rule for God in love and fear and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not as Lords over Gods heritage, and then you will engage all the honeſt and upright hearted in theſe Nations to ſubmit to your Government, not for wrath or fear of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but for Couſcience ſake; and this will be more honour to you and your Government, then if you could force every individual perſon both profeſſors &amp; prophane in the Nation to own you for fear of your wrath, for the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God, and the beſt effects of it will but make hypocrites for fear of puniſhment &amp; perſecution, if God do not perſwade the hearts of people by his Word and Spirit, &amp; ſubmit their ſpirits by his Power to very Ordinance of man both ſpiritual and temporal for the Lords ſake; they that were before you promiſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended much as in matter of Reformation, and removing of oppreſſion both in Church and State; but we may and do expect better things from you that have promiſed leſs, and not made ſo much ſhow of holineſs as they did, which if it ſo come to paſs the Lord ſhall have the glory, by whom you are permitted to bear Rule in the Nation, and you ſhall not looſe your reward, if you be found faithful in what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of you according to what you know; but if you walk in the ſteps of Tyrants and Oppreſſors, and ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, and perſecute tender Conſciences for and concerning the Law, and Worſhip of their God; Then What can you expect? But the ſame reward from him that is no reſpector of perſons, which they already have received that hated the reproofs of inſtruction, and the good and wholſom Advice and Councel from time to time directed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64021:7"/>unto them by theſe ſuffring ſervants of the Lord, that have all the day long been accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, who are coming up out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and travelling towards the Promiſed Land.</p>
            <p>Now if it be matter of Conſcience to one ſort of people in this Nation, or if it be ſuppoſed by them that the Book of Common Prayer or Divine Service ſo called, is the beſt way of Worſhip, and that they ſuppoſe it is well pleaſing and acceptable to the Lord, and from ſuch a perſwaſion they do determine to practice it in their Families, and in places of publick worſhip, then let them that are ſo perſwaded give liberty to others that are of another perſwaſion for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Conſciences according to their perſwafion and Principles, and let there be no fighting nor fining, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor impriſonment, nor no corporal Oath or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be inflicted on the bodies and eſtates of the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation, upon any Eccleſiaſtical or ſpiritual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, according to the true intent and meaning of the Act above-mentioned, and as the Law of God requires of every man to do unto others as he would have others to do unto him, and this will ſatisfie all the ſober-minded and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men in the Nation, and make way for a happy ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pure Religion, everlaſting Righteouſneſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect peace among people in matters relating to the Worſhip and Service of God, and in all things appertaining to the ſpiritual Kingdom and Government of Chriſt Jeſus, the chief ſhepherd and Biſhop of our Souls, whoſe right it is to reignes Supream head of the Church, who is the Authour, Finiſher and Defender of our Faith, and who is ſo to be owned eſpecially in this Nation by them who are of the the Proteſtant Religion, and who have denyed and proteſted againſt the Popes Supremacy and uſurpt Authority; and as his Supremacy and Authority is denyed, ſo let his Lawes &amp; Inſtitutions &amp; impoſitions be denyed alſo, that it may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly be declared that leſus Chriſt is the head of the Church, who is the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And they that are eſtabliſhed upon him have no need of the Turks Alcoran for a Rule to walk by, nor the Popes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64021:8"/>Maſs to teach them the knowledge of God and Chriſt; for God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in their hearts to teach them the knowledge of God and his Wayes, and they that have received the Spirit of God, and can pray with the Spirit, and with the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have no need of the Biſhops Book of compoſed or Common-payer, which is a ſet Form of words that every prophane perſon can repeat, for the Spirit it ſelf will help their infirmities that have received it, and make interceſſion unto God for the Saints and for Kings and all that are in Authority, and they that have this Spirit of God for a Rule to walk by, which is agreeable to the Scripture of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, they need not the Presbyters directory as a Rule for publick Worſhip, Church Ordinances and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, for the God of Order teacheth them how to walk and worſhip, and when to ſpeak and pray as they are moved by his Spirit, and in the Church of God they may all Prophecy one by one, and if any thing be revealed unto him that ſitteth by, the firſt is to hold his peace, for the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets, and there is no lording one over another, neither is the Spirit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or confined to him that has the higheſt place in the Aſſembly, for ſuch have taken away the Key of knowledge, and have forſaken the right Way, and are out of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, who are called of men Maſter, and have the chiefeſt ſeats in the Synagogues; and this is not the Order of the Churches of the Saints, but by them in this Order the Saints are perſecuted, and haled out of their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and before Magiſtrates; and the time of this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hath been long in which the pretended Leaders of the people in this Nation have cauſed them to err, and they that were led by them have been deſtroyed for want of the good knowledge of the Lord, for ſince the time that the right Way was forſaken, and the way of <hi>Baalam</hi> followed, the Prieſts have preached for hire, and they have taught fear towards God by the precepts of men; ſo that the unknown God hath been ignorantly worſhipped in the Old Maſs-houſes commonly called Churches, which is the invention and work of mens hands, and in which is the very ſeat of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64021:8"/>of jealouſie ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all manner of graven Images, Pictures and abominable Beaſts, and the ſimilitude of creeping things, and all the Idols of the houſe of <hi>Iſraels,</hi> portraied or painted round about upon the Walls, and in the higheſt places of theſe Idols Tempels have the Hirelings by Authority and Commiſſion from the higher Power made merchandize of the Scriptures, of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which were ſpoken forth free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the holy men of God in their day, and written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time not to be ſold for money; but for our learning and admonition upon whom the ends of the World is come; and becauſe we have declared againſt ſuch practiſes, we have been accuſed for denying the Scriptures and the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and becauſe we cannot own thoſe Maſs-houſes for Churches which were ſet up in the time of Popery, as the Idols Temples were ſet up when <hi>Iſrael</hi> had forgotten their Maker, and forſaken the fountain of living water, as its written in the Prophets, When <hi>Iſrael</hi> had forgotten her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſhe builded Temples, and <hi>Judah</hi> multiplied fenced Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; therefore we have been accuſed by the prophane and ignorant people, that we deny the Churches, becauſe we cannot contribute to the repairing of theſe painted houſes, in which are all theſe Pictures and Images portraied upon the Walls round about, and becauſe of theſe things by an uſurped Authority we have ſuffered the ſpoiling of our goods from time to time, and have been made as a prey to the teeth of mercileſs men, and becauſe for Conſcience ſake we could not come to theſe houſes to hear the Prieſts preach for hire, and ſo put into the mouth of the falſe prophet and Idol ſhepherds, we have been ſummoned by Law ſuites to <hi>London</hi> from all parts of this Nation, and have had our goods ſpoiled and our bodies impriſoned, ſome until death by a cruel hard-hearted generation of hireling Presbyterian Prieſts and Impropriators; ſo that we may truly ſay, Satans power hath been great, and the time hath been long in which he that could perſecute the People of God called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> by vertue of Authority derived from the higher Power, did think he did God good ſervice; but the Lord hath viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64021:9"/>and will vilit for theſe things, and with equity will he plead for the meek of the earth, and we have given our power and committed our cauſe unto him, ſo that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance is not upon the Arm of fleſh, or men of might, but in the Lord in whom there is Everlaſting ſtrength; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that you who are ſet up and intruſted amongſt men as the chief Authority in the Nation, may have precept up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on precept, and line upon line as others had in their day, a neceſſity is laid on the Lords Servants and Hand-maids, who loves not their lives unto the death, to ſpeak and write unto you of the things which they have ſeen and heard concerning you, as they are commanded of God, that to Gods witneſs in the ſight of the Lord they may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and that you may have warning in this your day not to touch the Lords annointed, nor to do any harm unto his Prophets, whether they be Sons or Daughters, Servants or Hand-maids upon whom God hath poured forth of his Spirit from on high in theſe latter dayes; And if it be in the hearts of you who are the preſent Rulers of this Nation, to ſettle &amp; eſtabliſh Religion as others have attempted to do, and ſo have limitted the Spirit of God by their Ordinances and Traditions, let it be wiſely conſidered whether God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſuch a thing at your hands, yea or nay; for many who were ſuppoſed to be Wiſe and Learned men, have been miſtaken in this very particular, and inſtead of Reformation they have brought in oppreſſion and perſecution, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a happy ſettlement they have cauſed great ſtrife, heart-burnings, diſputations and open contention about Church Ordinances, Worſhip, Doctrine and Diſcipline, and one ſort have cryed lo here is Chriſt, and others have ſaid here is the place where men ought to Worſhip, and others they cry this is the Good Old Way, let all be compelled to conform to this Way, and to our Order and Ordinances and Diſcipline, and let all be made ſubject to that Worſhip which our Fore-fathers owned, and to that Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which they lived under; and ſo would have all limitted to their Worſhip, and compelled to their way by corporal puniſhments, if for Conſcience ſake they cannot
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64021:9"/>be conformable; ſo that there is need of much wiſdome in this thing, &amp; the beſt way to preſerve peace in the Nation is to protect all people of all perſwafions alike in their Civil and Religious Rights, and not to compel any by force or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to any worſhip contrary to a full perſwaſion in their minds; for in this very Particular <hi>Jacobs</hi> Family hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all ſorts of people and governments of late in this Nation, both Parliaments, Protector, and profeſſors and prophane, and the Lords peculiar treaſure hath been tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon, as people not fit to be protected nor to live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth; and even like as the high-minded Councellors or Courtiers of the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> did in their day envy <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and incenſe the King againſt that people who were diſperſed in all the Provinces of his Kingdoms, as being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in their Laws from all other people, and that they did not obſerve the Kings Laws; even ſo have the proud and high-minded men in high Places in theſe dayes laboured to incenſe the Supream Magiſtrates againſt a diſperſed remnant of the Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whoſe captivity the Lord is returning out of the Land of the North Countrey, and out of all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they have been ſcattered, and we have been miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented both to Parliaments and others by the Prieſts of the high Places, as <hi>Amos</hi> was unto the King by <hi>Amaziah</hi> the Prieſt of <hi>Bethel,</hi> who ſent unto <hi>Jeroboam</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Amos</hi> hath conſpired againſt thee in the midſt of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the land is not able to bear his words, when he declared unto them that which the Lord had ſhewed unto him concerning them; and without all Controverſie ſome of our old Adverſaries by whom we have been perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ever ſince we were a people, may yet go about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade theſe preſent Rulers that it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer us to enjoy our Liberty and Religion within his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; and ſo wait for a Law from him to limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the uncircumciſed in all ages and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have done, and as the Rulers of this laſt age have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured and endeavoured to do, until the Lord hath made the Houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> as a fire, and the Houſe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> as a flame, and the Houſe of <hi>Eſau</hi> like ſtubble fully dry, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64021:10"/>hath conſumed their bryars and thorns as in one day; for the ſame ſpirit of envy remains yet unſatisfied in the Prieſts of the high Places, who prayed againſt the King and for the Protector, and cryed out for aſſiſtance, liek as the unbelieving Jews cryed, <hi>Men of Iſrael help, theſe are they that will turn the world upſide down:</hi> help <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>Parliament, Councel, Committee</hi> and <hi>Army;</hi> make your Law both <hi>Military</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> a defence of our Faith and Religion, Church Miniſtry and Ordinances, elſe theſe men that pretends the Motion of the Spirit, and immediate Revelation from Heaven, thoſe <hi>Quakers</hi> (that trembles at the Word of God) will prevail againſt us &amp; undermine the foundation of all our great Truths, and then not onely our Craft is in danger, by which we have got a livel, hood for our ſelves and Families, but alſo our <hi>Traditional Ordinances</hi> (and thoſe old Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes our Churches) in which are all theſe pleaſant pictures painted upon the Walls, and the glory of their magnificence will come into diſeſteem, and ſo by a corrupt new invented Law hath iniquity been eſtabliſhed, and the Saints of the moſt high perſecuted, and impriſoned for <hi>the Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the Word of God;</hi> and their Righteous Souls have cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>How long Lord? How long Holy and True? Wilt not thou Judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell upon the Earth?</hi> And becauſe Judgement was not ſpeedily executed upon the uſurpers of Authority &amp; workers of iniquity, and oppreſſors of the Juſt, all the falſe Prophets and bireling Prieſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed peace and ſafety to themſelves &amp; to the men in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and they were perſwaded that <hi>their Mountain was ſo invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible that it could never have been moved.</hi> Nay, all the chief ones of the Nation would not have believed that an enemy to their imperfect peace ſhould have entred into this Nation, to take all the antient high Places thereof again in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; But what ſhall we ſay to theſe things, the purpoſe of the Lord muſt come to paſs, <hi>That the oppreſſed may go free,</hi> and that the ſins of the falſe Prophets, and the imquity of the hireling Prieſts, and the corruption of Rulers may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, which is the Cauſe of all the Judgements of the Lord upon the Nation; for all the judgements which came upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who had neglected the day of their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64021:10"/>and mocked Gods Meſſengers, and ſtoned them that were ſent unto them, was for the ſins of the Prophets, and the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of her prieſts that ſhed the blood of the juſt in the midſt of her, that wandred as blind men in the ſtreets, and were pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with blood, ſo that they would not touch their garments, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.13. And this is the Cauſe of all theſe alterations and overturnings, which is ſo ſtrange and marvellous to the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that ſuch ſtrong men ſhould wax feeble and leave their glory to others, not by might nor by power, but by the Spirit of the Lord God, and according to his Word by his Servants the Prophets, whom they have mocked, deſpiſed, perſecuted and ſhameful entreated in the day of their proſperity and exaltation.</p>
            <p>But they would not receive inſtruction, and therefore muſt they receive correction; they would not be gathered, when the Lord would have gathered them as a Hen gathereth her Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens under her wings, and therefore are they ſcattered and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces; and that Stone which the Builders reſuſed, is become a Some of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence unto them, on which they are fallen and broken, and ſnared and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and whoſoever ſhall ſtrive with their Maker, and fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord ſhall not proſper nor prevail, for the Lord will thunder out of heaven upon his adverſaries, &amp; will break them to pieces; but this is the portion and heritage of his ſuffering Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whoſe Faith ſtands in his Power, &amp; whoſe Righteouſneſs is of him; every tongue that riſeth in Judgment againſt them ſhall be condemned, and this is the honour of all the Saints, to bind Kings in Chains, and Nobles with fetters of Iron, and to execute upon the Heathen the Judgements written, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8. For the Lord will not caſt off his People, neither will he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Inheritance, who are unto him as the Apple of his Eye, and whoſoever ſhall offend any of thoſe little ones, whoſe Faith ſtands in the Power of God, and who trembles at the Word of his Holineſs, <hi>It were better for him that a Mill-stone were hanged about his neck, and he drowned in the midst of the Sea;</hi> and though the wicked be highly exalted, and joyn hand and hand againſt the Seed which God hath bleſſed, yet muſt not they go unpuniſhed, though the Servants of the Lord be far from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or rendring unto them evil for evil; for although we were all the day long accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64021:11"/>have been ſmitten with the tongue of the uncircumciſed, and with the ſiſt of wickedneſs, &amp; every Horn of the Beaſts head hath puſhed at us from time to time, yet have we not deſired fire from Heaven to conſume our adverſaries, neither have we ſought to be avenged on them, or deſired their overthrow, God is witneſs for us; but we have loved them that hated us without a Cauſe, and we have prayed for them that perſecuted us, and to this day we deſire not their death, or that they ſhould be dealt with as they have dealt with others, and that their treſpaſtes may be forgiven them, more then they have forgiven others; and that the Lord would humble them in their afflictions, that they might return to him and know that the Moſt High Rules in the Kingdomes of men, who deſires not the death of ſinners, but rather that all men every where ſhould repent and come to the knowledge of his truth, for he waits to be gratious, becauſe he delights in the exerciſe of loving kindneſs, and there is mercy with him that he may be feared.</p>
            <p>And as for the ſtrange Act of the Lord which he hath brought to paſs ſo far, contrary to the expectation of many, who hath ſwept away the reſuge of lyes and the unrighteous covering, under which many were hid until the Lord appeared, who is bringing down the loftineſs of men that had ſet their neſts on high, and who were ready to ſay within themſelves every one in his own heart, <hi>I ſit as a Queen and ſhall ſee no more ſorrow, I'le aſcend into Heaven, and I will exalt my Throne above the ſtars of God, I will ſit alſo upon the Mount of the Congregation in the ſides of the North,</hi> whom God hath brought down into contempt, and near unto the ſides of the pit, and upon whom he hath brought theſe two things in one day, even deſolation, widow-hood and loſs of Children; let none rejoice over them, nor ſeek to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on them by killing their bodies or deſtroying their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, nor be lifted up by their fall, for all theſe things have happened unto them for examples unto ſuch as after all theſe things ſhall live ungodly, and lift up themſelves as Lords over Gods heritage; for all things that have happened unto them, &amp; all things written aforetime is for the admonition of theſe preſent Rolers &amp; this generation, that they may not ſit down to eat and drink and riſe up to play as in the dayes of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> for he that ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64021:11"/>Hell, and delivered them into Chains of darkneſs to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto Judgement; nor the old world that ſinned, who had corrupted their wayes upon the earth, but brought in the flood upon the world of the ungodly, and turned the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> into aſhes, condemning them with an overthrow for their ungodly deeds, 2. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> and he that cut off from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> both head and tail, branch and ruſh in one day, the antient and the honourable, he is the Head, and the Prophet that teacheth lyes, he is the tail, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.14. and who hath reproved Kings for the ſake of his People, ſaying, Touch not my annointed, and do my Prophets no harm, he is the ſame both in Juſtice and Power at this day, and his hand is not ſhortned, neither is he ſlack as ſome men count ſlackneſs, but will render a Juſt recompence of reward unto every man according to his works, whether they be good or evil, and the ſin of <hi>Sodom</hi> muſt not go unpuniſhed, for pride goes before deſtruction, and a high mind before a fall; therefore fear the Lord and tremble at the Word of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all ye Rulers and People upon the earth, and meet the Judge by the way, kiſs the Son, leaſt he be angry, if once his wrath be kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that puts their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Oh, who would not fear the King of Nations, whom God hath determined (by a perpetual Decree) to ſet upon the holy Hill of <hi>Zion;</hi> by whom Kings reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice, and who will <hi>Rule the Nations with a rod of Iron, and break them in pieces like a Potters Veſſel,</hi> And unto whom God will give <hi>the Heathen for an Inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the Earth for a Poſſeſſion;</hi> That the Government may be upon <hi>His Shoulder</hi> from generation to generation; of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of whoſe righteous Government and Peace there ſhall be <hi>no End:</hi> And unto him who hath been deſpiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected amongſt men, and whoſe Viſage hath been more mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, than any man, againſt whom the Kings of the Earth have ſhut their mouths, and ſaid, <hi>We will not have this man to Reign over us,</hi> Even unto this man of Sorrows, who is <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with grief,</hi> muſt all the ends of the earth look for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, And unto him muſt all the Kings of the Earth, and the Mighty men, and the chief Captains bring their glory,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64021:12"/>and their honour, and caſt their Crowns at his Feet; that He (whoſe Right it is) may have the Crown, and ſway the Scepter in the Kingdoms of men; and he muſt reign till <hi>All his Enemies be made his Foot-ſtool,</hi> and all <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Dominions, Principalities,</hi> and <hi>Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> muſt be made ſubject unto him; and they that will not have him to reign, muſt be be broken to pieces; And this is the Foundation which God hath laid in <hi>Zion,</hi> and <hi>Other Foundation can no man lay, then that which is laid,</hi> which is Jeſus Chriſt, the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and whoſoever believeth and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on him, ſhall never be aſhamed nor confounded; But they that believe not on him, ſhall ſtumble, and fall, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken; And this is the <hi>Rock,</hi> and <hi>Corner-Stone,</hi> which the Builders have refuſed, which to us is elect and precious, and is become the <hi>Head-Stone</hi> of the <hi>Corner,</hi> and the <hi>Top-Stone</hi> of that ſpiritual Building, which is <hi>fitly framed together, and is growing unto an holy Temple in the Lord;</hi> and that houſe which is builded on this Foundation, ſhall ſtand as Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> which cannot be moved; for it is not divided againſt it ſelf, neither can the Gates of Hell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt it; For whoſoever are eſtabliſhed in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe upon this <hi>Rock,</hi> are not ſoon ſhaken in minde, nor toſſed to and fro <hi>with every winde of Doctrine, by the ſlight of men, whereby they lie in wait</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Policy,, and cunning deviſed Fables <hi>to draw people from the hope of the Goſpel, and from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</hi> Neither doth theſe people (who are as <hi>Living ſtones</hi> or the ſpiritual houſe) cry to the Magiſtrates and outward Powers to have Religion ſetled by outward force, impoſing penalties upon <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> unto, and Diſturbers of their Way, and Worſhip, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; For they are already ſetled, and ſatisfied, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the true Religion, and in Righteouſneſs, and it is the Double-minded, who are <hi>unſtable like the Waters,</hi> and are toſſed to and fro like the <hi>troubled Sea,</hi> that are unſetled, and the beſt way to ſettle ſuch in the true Religion, or to leave them without excuſe, is to ſuffer the Miniſters of Gods Word to preach the Goſpel in the Power and Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, that the witneſſe of God may be raiſed in them, and the ſober Principle brought forth to rule men in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64021:13"/>matters both <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Civil;</hi> and this meek ſpirit and Principle is according to the will of God, and minde of Chriſt; And as this comes to be raiſed up by a powerful free Miniſtry, to rule in men, or in Families, Congregations, and Nations, ſo they come to be ſetled, and ſtayed, and builded up a ſpiritual houſe, that the Lord may dwel in them, as he hath ſaid, <hi>To this man will I look thats humble, and of a broken heart, and trembleth at my word, and I'le walk in them, and dwell in them</hi> (ſaith the Lord,) <hi>and they ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that which is required of you, is to keep the peace, and to be a Tertor to the Evil-doers, and not to ſuffer wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men to fight, and perſecute, and hale out of Aſſemblies, and ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe, nor to aſſault the people of God in their peaceable Meetings, and to ſuffer no fighting, nor ſtriking, nor impriſonment, nor killing men about Religion, and Worſhip, and Ordinances; For they that will fight and ſtrike about Religion, will never be ſettled in nor ſatisfied with any way of worſhip, until-their minds be changed, and their hands cleanſed and their hearts puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; neither will ſuch adorn the Goſpel by a good conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, under what name, pretence, or profeſſion ſoever; for that ſpirit is againſt every appearance of Truth in purity, and an enemy unto the Lord by wicked works</p>
            <p>Therefore all you who are in the High places of the earth, wait for counſel and direction from the Lord, how to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in this particular; and be not haſty to give conſent or encouragement to one ſort more then another, or to the people of one perſwaſion and judgement, to be as Lords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all others; for this hath proved the ruine and deſtruction of them whom the Lord hath caſt out before you: If you will be followers of Chriſt, and rule for God, you muſt be meek and lowly in heart, and take up the Croſſe to your own wills, that you may be found among the <hi>Lambs faithful followers,</hi> and numbred among <hi>the duſt of Jacob,</hi> whoſe Tents cannot be prevailed againſt by any Enchantment what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p>And now all people to whom this is directed, While the Candle of the Lord ſhineth upon your heads, and giveth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64021:14"/>Light unto you walk in the light thereof, and be not high-minded, nor ſelf-willed, nor ſoon angry, but fear the Lord, and follow after Righteouſneſſe and Truth, Peace and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſtrife (and contention, wars, and fightings, killing, and impriſoning about Religion, and Worſhip, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters maintenance) may ceaſe and come to an end; and let God in all things (relating to his Worſhip) have the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, and the ordering and diſpoſing of his People, that trembles at his word, and regards the opperation of his hand.</p>
            <p>And read this, and whatever elſe is directed unto you by the Lords faithful ſervants and Hand-maids, whom he moves as Inſtruments to make known his minde unto you; and neglect not the <hi>great ſalvation</hi> now begun to be ſpoken of; The door of Hope is open, and a price is put into your hands; ſleep not away your time, like the fooliſh <hi>Virgins,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Door be ſhut againſt you; Buy <hi>Oyl without money,</hi> that your <hi>Lamps may be trimmed and kept burning,</hi> that you may not ſtumble and fall upon the Rock of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> They that are fallen had a Day, and the Lord gave them warning, both by word and writing in their day, and this is your day in which the Lord waits to be gracious unto you, and his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long-ſuffering calls you to Repentance. Oh! that you did but know in this your day, the deſire &amp; breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lords ſervants for your Eternal good, and the things which doth belong unto your peace, and what it is that the Lord requires of you, yet a little while and the light is with you, whileſt you have it walk in it leaſt your candle be put out, and your Sun go down, and the ſhadows of the evening overtake you, whileſt you have an opertunity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe your ſelves as the ſervants of the Lord in doing good, and following after righteouſneſſe, for this is that which God requires of you all, from the leaſt unto the greateſt, to do juſtly, to love mercy, work Righteouſneſſe and walk humbly before him all the dayes of your appointed time, that he may be glorified by you in your life time, and you may have peace in your end.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kingſtone</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi>
                  <date>14. of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th month. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>T. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64021:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
